Guide to the Pauline Snedden Sears Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Pauline Snedden Sears papers
1931-1990
1953-1977
SC0501
Sears, Pauline Snedden.
2.5 Linear feet
Professional papers from her teaching career at Stanford University.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Pauline Sears, 1993.
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Associated Materials
Snedden Family Papers (SC1207)
Biography
Pauline (Pat) Sears earned her a.b. in psychology at Stanford in 1930, her M.A. in child guidance at Teachers College, Columbia University in 1931, and her Ph.D. in psychology at Yale University. Before joining the Stanford faculty in the School of Education in 1953, she taught at Yale and Harvard and was a research associate at the Child Welfare Research Station at the State University of Iowa. At Stanford she was promoted to assistant professor in 1955, associate professor in 1958, and full professor in 1966; she retired in 1973 with the rank of Emeritus Professor. While at Stanford, Prof. Sears was a research associate with the Stanford Center in Research and Development in Teaching. Her research subjects included the classroom effects of computer assisted instruction, development of creativity, and teaching strategies for effective reinforcement of culturally different children. In addition, she was administrator of the Elementary Teaching Training Program and organized the program in child development in the School of Education. Prof. Sears was the co-author of two books: In Pursuit of Self-Esteem and Intellectual Development.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Pauline Sears primarily pertain to her career at Stanford, with only one folder of materials pertaining to her activities during the 1930s. Included are correspondence, memoranda, proposals, papers, and articles. Her research interests include achievement motivation and creativity. Correspondents include Nicholas Anastasiow, Susan Crockenberg, David H. Feldman, Lilian Katz, and Joanne Gamble Whitmore. The papers have been arranged in three sections: general files, works by Sears, and files on students and/or colleagues. The correspondence is generally both incoming and outgoing.
Access Terms
Anastasiow, Nicholas; Crockenberg, Susan; Feldman, David H.; Katz, Lilian; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; Whitmore, Joanne Gamble; Education--Study and teaching; Motivation (Psychology)
Collection Contents
- General Files, 1931-1990
  - Achievement motivation project - proposal, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical materials (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Case study reports by students in psychology class, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence regarding death of friends, 1984-89 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to the Gamble's, 1970 and undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence regarding professional matters, 1968-90 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with students, 1967-72 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with students, 1973-74 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Christmas cards and misc. notes (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1970-85 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous items (exams, notes, clipping), 1931-37 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pursuit of Self-Esteem - comments on (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Professional papers (memoranda, correspondence, budgets, vita), 1957-75 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Professional papers (memoranda, correspondence, reports, vita), 1957-75 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sears, David - articles (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sears, David - articles (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sears, Robert - death of (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Works by Pauline Sears, 1959-1972
  - Book reviews (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Classroom work behavior of children, by Sears and Margaret H. Pintler, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Effect of classroom conditions on the strength of achievement motive and work output on elementary school children; Cooperative research project no. 873, 1963; two mimeographed papers (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Effect of classroom conditions on the strength of achievement motive and work output on elementary school children; Cooperative research project no. 873, 1963; [bound volume] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Effective reinforcement for achievement behaviors in disadvantaged children: the first year; Stanford Center for Research and Development in Teaching, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Effects of computer assisted instruction on children's behavior, by Sears and David H. Feldman; Educational Technology, March, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Implications of motivation theory for independent learning; conference paper, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - A look at measures of achievement motivation, symposium paper, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pursuit of self-esteem: the middle childhood years, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Self concept in the service of educational goals, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Study of development of creativity: research problems in parental antecedents, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Teachers' interactions with boys and with girls, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Teacher's role in the motivation of the learner, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - What happens to pupils within the classroom in elementary schools?, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Students and Colleagues Files, 1956-1977
  - Anastasiow, Nicholas - articles (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Anastasiow, Nicholas - articles (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Anastasiow, Nicholas - correspondence and poems, 1969-75 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Compton, Carolyn, 1967-70 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Crist, Janet, 1972-74 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Crockenberg, Susan - articles and papers, 1976-77 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Crockenberg, Susan - correspondence, 1970-76 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Feldman, David - correspondence, 1972-75 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Feldman, David - articles and papers (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Firme, Thereza Penna, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Katz, Lilian - reprints and published articles (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Katz, Lilian - articles from ERIC Clearinghouse (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Katz, Lilian - typescript articles (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Katz, Lilian - correspondence, 1968-73 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - King, Donald, 1969-71 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Leler, Hazel, 1969-75 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Levin, Harry, 1956-57 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lewittes, Hedva, 1971-73 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mbilinyi, Marjorie, 1968, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - McFee, June, 1972-75 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mote, Florence, 1963, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mwaniki, Mebo K., 1970-73 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Nichols, Sherry, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Nieman, Marianne, 1969, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Peters, Don, 1968-74 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pirofski, Florence, 1969-76 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Reimanis, Gunars, 1967-68 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Schwartz, Pauline, 1972-74 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Smith, Helen, 1971-76 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Smith, Ian, 1970-71 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Trickett, Helen, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Vint, Virginia, 1963-74 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Whitmore, Joanne Gamble, 1969-73 (Box 5, Folder 17)